Guide to the Jeannette Hopkins Papers, 1922-2011
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Jeannette Hopkins Papers,
1922-2011
Hopkins, Jeanette, 1922-
23 cubic feet (20 boxes, 5 volumes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Papers concern Hopkins' work on behalf of authors as an editor and agent and include correspondence, memoranda, contract summaries, and production records; correspondence often includes extensive discussion of a book's ideas, of changes and alterations, and of public response. Authors include Ben H. Bagdikian, Robert Bendiner, James MacGregor Burns, Marquis W. Childs, Eugene Genovese, Leonard W. Levy, Frank Mankiewicz, Edwin Newman, and Stan Steiner.
Biographical Note
Jeannette Hopkins (VC 1944) was born in Camden, NJ in 1922. She received an M.S. from the Columbia School of Journalism in 1945. After six years in journalism, in 1952 she turned to editing, and was employed successfully by Beacon Press, Harcourt Brace & World, and Harper & Row. In 1973 Miss Hopkins set up an independent service as a consulting editor for a number of publishing houses, including Harper & Row, McGraw-Hill, MacMillan, Random House, and Yale. She was appointed director of the Wesleyan University Press in 1980.
Miss Hopkins was active in the Unitarian church and had a particularly interest in public affairs such as civil liberties and race relations. With Kenneth B. Clark she was the co-author of A Relevant War Against Poverty. She died August 4, 2011.
Scope and Content Note
Papers concern Hopkins' work on behalf of authors as an editor and agent and include correspondence, memoranda, contract summaries, and production records; correspondence often includes extensive discussion of a book's ideas, of changes and alterations, and of public response. Authors include Ben H. Bagdikian, Robert Bendiner, James MacGregor Burns, Marquis W. Childs, Eugene Genovese, Leonard W. Levy, Frank Mankiewicz, Edwin Newman, and Stan Steiner. Scrapbooks include material relating to her editing work as well as her time as a student at Vassar College.
Access
There is restricted material in boxes 1, 2, 9 and 12. The rest of the collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Bagdikian, Ben H.; Bendiner, Robert; Burns, James MacGregor; Childs, Marquis William, 1903-; Genovese, Eugene D., 1930-; Levy, Leonard Williams, 1923-; Mankiewicz, Frank, 1924-; Newman, Edwin; Steiner, Stan
Subjects:
Publishers and publishing; Authors; Editors; Literary agents
Organizations:
Vassar College--Students
VCL Categories
Printing and Publishing
Encoding Information
Original encoding by Elizabeth Clarke, February 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jeannette Hopkins and her estate. The material came in several accessions from 1977-2013.
Container List
- Files
  - Restricted Material (Boxes 1-2)
  - Harcourt Brace — Sample editorial reports, 1956-1964 (Box 3)
  - Harcourt Brace — Correspondence upon leaving, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Harcourt Brace — Editorial meeting reports, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence — A-Ho, ca. 1964-1980 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence — Hu-Sh, ca. 1964-1980 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence — Si-Z, ca. 1964-1980 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence — Miscellaneous, ca. 1964-1980 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence — B-C, ca. 1970-1980 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence — D-W, ca. 1970-1980 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence — Lewis Mumford, ca. 1960-1963 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence — General Authors, ca. 1960-1990 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence — B-T, ca. 1960-1990 (Box 7)
  - Wesleyan University (Box 7)
  - Wesleyan University Press (Box 7)
  - Wesleyan University Press (Box 8)
  - Freelance (Box 8)
  - University of New Hampshire (Box 8)
  - University Press of New England (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous publishers (Box 8)
  - Documentary text book (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, ca. 1995-2005 (Box 9)
  - Stephen Hess (Box 9)
  - Equal Educational Opportunity (Box 9)
  - Reviews of books edited by Hopkins (Box 9)
  - Poems by Jeannette Hopkins (Box 9)
  - Fox-Genovese (Box 9)
  - Genovese (Box 9)
  - Lasch, Christopher (Box 9)
  - Rovere, Richard (Box 9)
  - Seminar: "How to Transform a Dissertation into a Book" [RESTRICTED] (Box 9)
  - Hopkins' manuscript: "The Whole Thing: The Author, the Editor, and the Book" (Boxes 10-12)
  - Hopkins' miscellaneous writings (Box 12)
  - Wesleyan University Press (Box 12)
  - Beacon Press (Box 12)
  - Correspondence and Proposals, ca. 2005-2011; [RESTRICTED] (Box 12)
  - "Poets to Write to" (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous personal (Box 13)
  - Family and genealogy (Box 13)
  - FOIA request (Box 13)
  - Vassar College (Box 13)
  - Diplomas (Box 13)
  - Charles Sherover (Box 13)
  - Portsmouth (Box 13)
  - Unfiled scrapbook material (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Mumford, Lewis (Box 14)
- Scrapbooks
  - Vassar College, ca. 1940-1944; (2 volumes) (Box 14)
  - Vassar College, (2 volumes) (Unboxed)
  - New Haven Register, 1945-1946 (Box 15)
  - Providence Journal and Bulletin, 1946-1950 (Box 15)
  - Oklahoma City Times, 1950-1951 (Box 15)
  - Beacon Press/Campaign (Box 16)
  - Beacon Press, 1951-1956 (Box 16)
  - Harcourt, 1956-1964; (2 volumes) (Box 17)
  - Harper and Row, 1964-1973; (2 volumes) (Box 18)
  - New York City freelance, 1973-1980 (Box 19)
  - Politics I, 1930s-1950s (Box 19)
  - Politics II, 1960s-1972 (Box 20)
  - Politics III, 1970s-1980s, 1992-1996 (Box 20)
  - Politics IV, 2000- (Box 16)
  - Material housed with "Politics IV" Scrapbook that predates its contents, 1922-2000 (Box 16)
    Includes letters from:
    Bryan, William Jennings (to Carleton Hopkins), 4 Feb 1922
    Roosevelt, Eleanor, 13 Oct 1945
    Bowles, Chester, 14 May 1953
    Stevenson, Adlai, 10 Feb 1959
    Lincoln, Evelyn, n.d.
    Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr., 2 Dec 1963
    McGovern, George, 2 Apr 1965, 29 Jan 1971
    Kennedy, Robert F. 12 July 1965
    Supreme Court Justices (Black, Warren, Brennan and Fortas), 1965
    Humphrey, Hubert, 1966-1967 (4 letters and 1 carbon)
    Bunche, Ralph, 11 Jan 1966
    Supreme Court Justices (Warren, Harlan, Stewart, White Brennan and Fortas), 1966
    Tuckerman, Nancy (on behalf of Jacqueline Kennedy), 31 July 1967
    Oppenheimer, Robert, 30 June 1966
    Muskie, Edmund, 28 Apr 1969
    Hoover, J. Edgar, 10 Feb 1969
    Buchanan, Partick, 1 Mar 1972
    Rumsfeld, Donald, 29 Feb 1972
    Kennedy, Edward, 15 March 1976
    Rusk, Dean, 18 Aug 1977
    Bork, Robert, 3 Sep 1987
    Clinton, Bill, 3 Nov 2000
    Miscellaneous letters from political figures
    Political ephemera
    Empty envelopes from the White House
  - Wesleyan Authors (Unboxed)
  - ACLU Board (Unboxed)
  - MARC, ACLU, NAACP, and the Coleman Report (Unboxed)